<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
 <title>The Third Bit</title>
 <link href="https://third-bit.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="/"/>
 <updated>2025-01-03T00:00:00Z</updated>
 <id>https://third-bit.com/</id>
 <author>
   <name>Greg Wilson</name>
   <email>gvwilson@third-bit.com</email>
 </author>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Time Management</title>
   <link href="https://third-bit.com/2025/01/03/time-management/"/>
   <updated>2025-01-03T00:00:00Z</updated>
   <id>https://third-bit.com/2025/01/03/time-management/</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;My &lt;a href=&#34;https://third-bit.com/2025/01/02/crunch-mode/&#34;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt; explained why people are most productive
when they work at a steady pace and get lots of rest,
and [&lt;a href=&#34;https://dl.acm.org/doi/10.1145/1584322.1584325&#34;&gt;Edwards2009&lt;/a&gt;] found that
starting assignments early and working consistently predicted good grades.
However,
while people in industry joke that having two bosses means living in hell,
students usually answer to four or five professors
whom don&amp;rsquo;t coordinate due dates across their courses.
I remember a week where I had two major assignments due,
two mid-terms to write,
and a bad cold;
what can you do when this happens to you?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best solution—or more honestly, the least bad—is to prioritize carefully.
Get a piece of paper and draw a 3×3 grid.
The X axis is effort: label its divisions &amp;ldquo;minutes&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;hours&amp;rdquo;, and &amp;ldquo;days&amp;rdquo;.
The Y axis is time: label it &amp;ldquo;low&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;medium&amp;rdquo;, and &amp;ldquo;high&amp;rdquo;.
You should wind up with something like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://third-bit.com/files/2025/effort-importance.svg&#34; alt=&#34;effort-importance grid&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next,
put everything you need to do somewhere on the grid,
and then throw away the high-effort, low-importance items in the bottom right—you
aren&amp;rsquo;t going to get to those.
You can then start assembling the other items into a schedule,
starting with the upper-left corner.
These are the things that will give the highest return on invested time;
more importantly,
starting with these means that if you&amp;rsquo;ve under-estimated effort,
you will still deliver &lt;em&gt;something&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The tricky items are the ones on the diagonal.
Should you tackle one thing that is high effort and high importance
or three things that are individually less important
but require the same total effort?
Laying things out on a grid can&amp;rsquo;t answer that question,
but at least it can tell you what the question is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;callout&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How to prioritize:
always finish first the tasks that will allow other people to continue/start/finish their work.
&lt;br&gt;
— &lt;a href=&#34;https://yabellini.netlify.app/&#34;&gt;Yanina Bellini Saibene&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If any task on your list is more than an hour long,
break it down into smaller pieces and prioritize those separately.
Figuring out what those pieces are can take time,
so don&amp;rsquo;t be embarrassed to make &amp;ldquo;plan XYZ&amp;rdquo; a task in its own right.
And remember that the future is approaching at a rate of 24 hours per day:
if something is going to take thirty hours to finish,
you had better allow at least five working days for it,
which means you&amp;rsquo;d better start at least that far ahead of the deadline.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The point of all this organization and preparation is
to be able to immerse yourself in your problem.
[&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.harpercollins.com/products/flow-mihaly-csikszentmihalyi&#34;&gt;Csikszentmihalyi1991&lt;/a&gt;] popularized the term flow for this;
athletes call it &amp;ldquo;being in the zone&amp;rdquo;,
while musicians talk about losing themselves in what they&amp;rsquo;re playing.
The good news is that you&amp;rsquo;re much more productive in this state
than when you&amp;rsquo;re multi-tasking.
The bad news is that
it takes anywhere from several seconds to several minutes
to get back into this state after an interruption [&lt;a href=&#34;https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s11219-010-9104-9&#34;&gt;Parnin2010&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://dl.acm.org/doi/10.1145/2702123.2702156&#34;&gt;Borst2015&lt;/a&gt;].
In other words,
if you are interrupted half a dozen times per hour
you are &lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt; at your productive peak.
Ironically,
the cost of self-interruptions may be even worse than the cost for external interruptions [&lt;a href=&#34;https://dl.acm.org/doi/10.1145/3210459.3210471&#34;&gt;Abad2018&lt;/a&gt;].&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;callout&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Open offices suck&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Open offices were created
so that (mostly male) managers could keep an eye on (mostly female) office workers,
and to reduce air conditioning costs [&lt;a href=&#34;https://isbnsearch.org/isbn/9780140169126&#34;&gt;Eley1995&lt;/a&gt;].
They lower productivity in every other way we can measure [&lt;a href=&#34;https://royalsocietypublishing.org/doi/10.1098/rstb.2017.0239&#34;&gt;Bernstein2018&lt;/a&gt;];
sadly,
the same is true of other interruption-rich environments
like your favorite coffee shop.
If you really want to be productive,
you should avoid both.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally,
you will be more productive in the long run if your back doesn&amp;rsquo;t ache,
and being away from the keyboard
gives your brain a chance to reflect on what you&amp;rsquo;ve just been doing.
You should therefore take a five-minute break every hour.
Checking email doesn&amp;rsquo;t count:
get up and stretch,
refill your water bottle,
or go and restack the dishwasher.
You&amp;rsquo;ll be amazed at how often you can solve a problem that&amp;rsquo;s been baffling you for an hour
by taking a short walk.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Crunch Mode</title>
   <link href="https://third-bit.com/2025/01/02/crunch-mode/"/>
   <updated>2025-01-02T00:00:00Z</updated>
   <id>https://third-bit.com/2025/01/02/crunch-mode/</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m supervising some undergraduate students at the University of Toronto this semester.
It&amp;rsquo;s the first time I&amp;rsquo;ve done this in almost 15 years,
and it&amp;rsquo;s giving me a chance to re-think and re-write the advice I used to give
when I was doing this regularly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;callout&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My starting point is [&lt;a href=&#34;http://dx.doi.org/10.1109/icse.2017.20&#34;&gt;Sedano2017&lt;/a&gt;],
which found that software development projects have nine types of waste:
building the wrong feature or product,
mismanaging the backlog,
rework,
unnecessarily complex solutions,
extraneous cognitive load,
psychological distress,
waiting and multitasking,
knowledge loss,
and ineffective communication.
&lt;em&gt;None of these are software issues,&lt;/em&gt;
so if you only think about the code in your project and not about the people writing it,
everything will take longer and hurt more than it needs to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I used to brag about the hours I was working.
Not in so many words, of course—I had &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; social skills—but
I&amp;rsquo;d show up for work around noon,
unshaven and yawning,
and casually mention how I&amp;rsquo;d been up until 6:00 a.m. working on some monster bug.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking back,
I can&amp;rsquo;t remember who I was trying to impress.
Instead,
what I remember is how much of the code I wrote in those all-nighters I threw away
once I&amp;rsquo;d had some sleep.
My mistake was to confuse &amp;ldquo;long hours&amp;rdquo; with &amp;ldquo;getting things done&amp;rdquo;.
You can&amp;rsquo;t produce software (or anything else) without doing some work,
but you can easily do lots of work without producing anything of value.
Scientific study of overwork goes back to at least the 1890s—see
[&lt;a href=&#34;https://igda.org/resources-archive/why-crunch-mode-doesnt-work-six-lessons-2005/&#34;&gt;Robinson2005&lt;/a&gt;] for a short, readable summary.
The most important results are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Working more than eight hours a day for more than a couple of weeks of time
    lowers your total productivity,
    not just your hourly productivity—i.e., you get less done &lt;em&gt;in total&lt;/em&gt; in crunch mode
    than when you work regular hours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Working over 21 hours in a stretch
    increases the odds of you making a catastrophic error
    just as much as being legally drunk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These facts have been verified through hundreds of experiments
over the course of more than a century,
including some on novice software developers [&lt;a href=&#34;https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/8357494&#34;&gt;Fucci2020&lt;/a&gt;].
The data behind them is as solid as the data linking smoking to lung cancer.
However,
while most smokers will at least acknowledge that their habit is killing them,
people in the software industry still talk and act as if
they were somehow immune to science.
To quote Robinson&amp;rsquo;s article:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;callout&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When Henry Ford famously adopted a 40-hour workweek in 1926,
he was bitterly criticized by members of the National Association of Manufacturers.
But his experiments,
which he&amp;rsquo;d been conducting for at least 12 years,
showed him clearly that cutting the workday from ten hours to eight hours—and
the workweek from six days to five days—increased
total worker output and reduced production cost…
the core of his argument was that reduced shift length meant more output.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;…many studies,
conducted by businesses, universities, industry associations and the military,
…support the basic notion that,
for most people,
eight hours a day,
five days per week,
is the best sustainable long-term balance point between output and exhaustion.
Throughout the 30s, 40s, and 50s, these studies were apparently conducted by the hundreds;
and by the 1960s,
the benefits of the 40-hour week were accepted almost beyond question in corporate America.
In 1962,
the Chamber of Commerce even published a pamphlet extolling the productivity gains of reduced hours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, somehow, Silicon Valley didn&amp;rsquo;t get the memo…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I spent two years at a data visualization startup.
Three months before our first release,
the head of development &amp;ldquo;asked&amp;rdquo; us to start coming in on Saturdays.
We were already pulling one late night a week at that point
(without overtime pay—our boss seemed to think that
ten dollars&amp;rsquo; worth of pizza
was adequate compensation for four hours of work)
and most of us were also working at least a couple of hours at home in the evenings.
To no one&amp;rsquo;s surprise,
we missed our &amp;ldquo;can&amp;rsquo;t miss&amp;rdquo; deadline by ten weeks,
and had to follow up our 1.0 release with a 1.1 and then a 1.2
to fix the crash-and-lose-data bugs we&amp;rsquo;d created.
We were all zombies, and zombies can&amp;rsquo;t code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hours like these are sadly still normal in many parts of the software industry,
and may actually be worse now that so many people are working from home.
Designing and building software is a creative act that requires a clear head;
it only takes a couple of minutes to create a bug
that will take hours to track down later.
As Robinson writes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;callout&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Productivity varies over the course of the workday,
with the greatest productivity occurring in the first four to six hours.
After enough hours,
productivity approaches zero;
eventually it becomes negative.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s hard to quantify the productivity of programmers, testers, and UI designers
[&lt;a href=&#34;https://link.springer.com/book/10.1007/978-1-4842-4221-6&#34;&gt;Sadowski2019&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://dl.acm.org/doi/10.1145/3454122.3454124&#34;&gt;Forsgren2021&lt;/a&gt;],
but five eight-hour days per week has been proven to maximize long-term total output
in every industry that has ever been studied.
There is no reason to believe that ours is any different.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ah, you say, but that&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;long-term&lt;/em&gt; output.
What about short bursts now and then,
like pulling an all-nighter to meet a deadline?
That&amp;rsquo;s been studied too,
and the results aren&amp;rsquo;t pleasant [&lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/1805.02544&#34;&gt;Fucci2018&lt;/a&gt;].
Your ability to think drops by 25 points for each 24 hours you&amp;rsquo;re awake.
Put it another way,
the average person&amp;rsquo;s IQ is only 75 after one all-nighter,
which puts them in the bottom 5% of the population.
Two all nighters in a row and their effective IQ is 50—the level at which
people are considered incapable of independent living.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The catch in all of this is that people usually don&amp;rsquo;t notice their abilities declining.
Just like drunks who think they&amp;rsquo;re still able to drive,
people who are deprived of sleep don&amp;rsquo;t realize that they&amp;rsquo;re not finishing their sentences (or thoughts).
They certainly don&amp;rsquo;t realize that they&amp;rsquo;re calling functions with parameters in the wrong order
or that the reason the tests are failing is that
they&amp;rsquo;ve forgotten to redeploy the application—again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first and most important lesson is therefore
to think about what&amp;rsquo;s more important—how much you produce
or how much of a martyr you appear to be—and to pace yourself accordingly.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Cross One Off My List</title>
   <link href="https://third-bit.com/2024/12/30/cross-one-off-my-list/"/>
   <updated>2024-12-30T00:00:00Z</updated>
   <id>https://third-bit.com/2024/12/30/cross-one-off-my-list/</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Thanks to a recommendation from &lt;a href=&#34;https://jefframnani.com/&#34;&gt;Jeff Ramnani&lt;/a&gt;,
I borrow &lt;a href=&#34;https://laurspilca.com/&#34;&gt;Laurenţiu Spilcă&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.manning.com/books/troubleshooting-java&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Troubleshooting Java&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
from my local public library,
and am very glad I did.
The book delivers exactly what the title offers:
a step-by-step guide to finding and fixing problems in Java applications
using everything from breakpointing debuggers to profilers and specialized visualization tools.
I hope peopple are inspired by it to write equivalent books for JavaScript, Python, and other languages,
but even if that doesn&amp;rsquo;t happen,
I&amp;rsquo;m glad to be able to cross one book off my &lt;a href=&#34;https://third-bit.com/ideas/not-on-the-shelves/2024/&#34;&gt;unwritten list&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;center&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://third-bit.com/files/2024/troubleshooting-java.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;cover of &#39;Troubleshooting Java&#39;&#34; width=&#34;25%&#34;&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Jimmy Carter</title>
   <link href="https://third-bit.com/2024/12/29/jimmy-carter/"/>
   <updated>2024-12-29T00:00:00Z</updated>
   <id>https://third-bit.com/2024/12/29/jimmy-carter/</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;div class=&#34;center&#34;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://third-bit.com/files/2024/jimmy-carter.webp&#34; alt=&#34;Jimmy Carter&#34; width=&#34;50%&#34;&gt;
    &lt;br&gt;
    1924 - 2024
  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Being a Great Teacher</title>
   <link href="https://third-bit.com/2024/12/28/being-a-great-teacher/"/>
   <updated>2024-12-28T00:00:00Z</updated>
   <id>https://third-bit.com/2024/12/28/being-a-great-teacher/</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Three keys to being a great teacher:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Have students who are safe and well nourished,
    not victims of systemic discrimination,
    and live in supportive home environments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Work in an educational system that has stable long-term funding
    and is administered by people who respect your professional expertise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ignore posts that put all the responsibility for being a great teacher on you
    rather than saying that collective action to achieve #1 and #2 are what will actually make a difference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Engagement</title>
   <link href="https://third-bit.com/2024/12/28/engagement/"/>
   <updated>2024-12-28T00:00:00Z</updated>
   <id>https://third-bit.com/2024/12/28/engagement/</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A junk &amp;ldquo;study&amp;rdquo; about &amp;ldquo;ghost engineers&amp;rdquo; popped up a few weeks ago claiming that 9.5% of software developers do nothing.
The author, Yegor Denisov-Blanch, has consistently dodged questions about methodology and refused to share data,
but I&amp;rsquo;m willing to bet his work has been seen by more practitioners in the past 30 days
than every careful, peer-reviewed piece of empirical software engineering research published this year.
I think it would be very cool if an enterprising grad student proved this,
i.e.,
estimated the number of times Denisov-Blanch&amp;rsquo;s work has been viewed or mentioned
and compared it to the number of views and mentions of work from ICSE or &lt;em&gt;Empirical Software Engineering&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More importantly,
I think the software engineering research community should ask themselves
why stuff like this gets so much attention when their work doesn&amp;rsquo;t,
and ask themselves what they should do in order to have that kind of impact.
Public health researchers are doing this kind of critical reflection right now
to figure out how anti-vaccination conspiracy theories have displaced actual science in so many people&amp;rsquo;s minds
so that they can fight back;
if people who study software and software developers want to do more than just observe—if they want
to have some actual impact—I think they would do well to look at why bullshit finds such a large audience.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Not Very Scalable</title>
   <link href="https://third-bit.com/2024/12/27/not-very-scalable/"/>
   <updated>2024-12-27T00:00:00Z</updated>
   <id>https://third-bit.com/2024/12/27/not-very-scalable/</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I have been teaching some informal lessons to colleagues based on
the Python version of &lt;a href=&#34;https://third-bit.com/sdxpy/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Software Design by Example&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;,
and one thing that has bothered me is the sizing of the diagrams.
It&amp;rsquo;s not too bad in a chapter like &lt;a href=&#34;https://third-bit.com/sdxpy/glob/&#34;&gt;this one&lt;/a&gt;,
but when those same SVG files are displayed in &lt;a href=&#34;https://third-bit.com/sdxpy/glob/slides/#2&#34;&gt;slides like these&lt;/a&gt;
they are a bit hard to read.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I thought the solution would be simple:
&amp;ldquo;SVG&amp;rdquo; stands for &amp;ldquo;Scalable Vector Graphics&amp;rdquo;,
so I should just be able to apply a scaling factor via CSS to enlarge the diagrams
when they are displayed in slide files.
(Modifying the source isn&amp;rsquo;t an option:
they are all carefully sized for the print edition,
and I&amp;rsquo;m not going to duplicate 107 diagrams to solve what is in reality a minor annoyance.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But what scaling factor should I apply and how should I apply it?
I can&amp;rsquo;t specify an absolute width or a page-relative fraction:
the source diagrams have different intrinsic sizes,
so either of those options would result in different diagrams being scaled by different amounts.
Doing this wouldn&amp;rsquo;t actually be so bad if they just contained lines,
but they all have text as well,
and if some of the diagrams are effectively scaled from (for example) 12-point to 15-point
while others are scaled from 12-point to 18-point,
it really stands out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s worse is that when I scale up the SVG by a fixed amount (e.g., 120%)
it overlaps with the text below it.
A bit of poking around revealed that the browser lays out the text on the slide
using the SVG&amp;rsquo;s original (intrinsic) size,
and &lt;em&gt;then&lt;/em&gt; resizes the SVG.
It isn&amp;rsquo;t noticeable if the figure is the last or only thing on the slide,
but that&amp;rsquo;s not always the case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best solution so far comes from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/camerondecoster/&#34;&gt;Cameron DeCoster&lt;/a&gt;,
and relies on the fact that all of these SVG images are contained in &lt;code&gt;figure&lt;/code&gt; elements:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nd&#34;&gt;root&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;w&#34;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;w&#34;&gt;     &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nv&#34;&gt;--image-width&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;w&#34;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;80&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;kt&#34;&gt;%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;nt&#34;&gt;figure&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nc&#34;&gt;fullwidth&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;w&#34;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nt&#34;&gt;img&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;w&#34;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;w&#34;&gt;    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;width&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;w&#34;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;100&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;kt&#34;&gt;%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&#34;nt&#34;&gt;img&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nc&#34;&gt;centered&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;w&#34;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;w&#34;&gt;    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;display&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;w&#34;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;kc&#34;&gt;block&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;w&#34;&gt;    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;margin-left&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;w&#34;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;kc&#34;&gt;auto&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;w&#34;&gt;    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;margin-right&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;w&#34;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;kc&#34;&gt;auto&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;nt&#34;&gt;img&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nc&#34;&gt;image&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;w&#34;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;w&#34;&gt;    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;width&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;w&#34;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nf&#34;&gt;var&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nv&#34;&gt;--image-width&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&#34;nt&#34;&gt;img&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nc&#34;&gt;scaled-img&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;w&#34;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;w&#34;&gt;    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;c&#34;&gt;/*&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;c&#34;&gt;    Setting the width to a percentage increases the size of the of&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;c&#34;&gt;    the image, but the width of the image is calculated using the&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;c&#34;&gt;    intrinsic size during the initial layout phase and doesn&amp;#39;t get&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;c&#34;&gt;    updated as the image is scaled up.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;c&#34;&gt;    (https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Glossary/Intrinsic_Size)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;c&#34;&gt;    */&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;w&#34;&gt;    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;width&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;w&#34;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;120&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;kt&#34;&gt;%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&#34;w&#34;&gt;    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;c&#34;&gt;/*&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;c&#34;&gt;    Setting the width to an explicit number provides an&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;c&#34;&gt;    independent container element and everything works correctly.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;c&#34;&gt;    */&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;w&#34;&gt;    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;c&#34;&gt;/* width: 500px; */&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&#34;w&#34;&gt;    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;c&#34;&gt;/* &lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;c&#34;&gt;    Using a scale transform increases the size of the image but&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;c&#34;&gt;    doesn&amp;#39;t update the page layout.  As such, the image element&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;c&#34;&gt;    will begin to overlap surrounding elements at higher scales.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;c&#34;&gt;    */&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;w&#34;&gt;    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;c&#34;&gt;/* transform: scale(1.6); */&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s still not perfect:
as the image below shows,
the rescaled figure is no longer centered.
As Cameron explains:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The centering issue is due to the fact that there&amp;rsquo;s a cyclic dependency between two elements:
the image and the container.
Using flexbox on the figure with center justified content means that
the content of the container (the image) will set the width.
However, we&amp;rsquo;re using a percentage for the width on the image,
which depends on the width of the parent (the container).
The W3C resolves this as stated &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.w3.org/TR/css-sizing-3/#cyclic-percentage-contribution&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
The result is that the initial width calculation is performed using the original size of the image,
then the container is centered,
then the image is scaled.
Unfortunately,
that means that the image centering calculation is done with a different width than the image we see,
and things look wonky.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;center&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://third-bit.com/files/2024/decoster-css.png&#34; alt=&#34;DeCoster CSS example&#34; width=&#34;90%&#34;&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SVG is now 25 years old.
I think &amp;ldquo;scale this up&amp;rdquo; ought to be a lot easier than it is,
but my real gripe is that I have no idea how the average person
would ever figure this out.
If you want to play around with a small example,
please check out &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/gvwilson/resize-demo&#34;&gt;this repository&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Wrapping Up the Year</title>
   <link href="https://third-bit.com/2024/12/15/wrapping-up-the-year/"/>
   <updated>2024-12-15T00:00:00Z</updated>
   <id>https://third-bit.com/2024/12/15/wrapping-up-the-year/</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Another year, another look back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What I Did&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I left &lt;a href=&#34;https://third-bit.com/2024/04/05/moving-on/&#34;&gt;Deep Genomics&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://third-bit.com/2024/04/29/new-job-at-plotly/&#34;&gt;joined Plotly&lt;/a&gt;,
    where I deleted several hundred GitHub repositories
    and closed several thousand stale issues.
    I still enjoy coding and teaching more than I enjoy managing,
    but most tech companies don&amp;rsquo;t realize they need teachers,
    and most seem uncomfortable when faced with 61-year-olds who want to code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Python version of &lt;a href=&#34;https://third-bit.com/sdxpy/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Software Design by Example&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; came out.
    Reviewers seemed to like it,
    but sales and website traffic have been disappointing.
    I don&amp;rsquo;t know if it&amp;rsquo;s because I&amp;rsquo;m not working hard enough to get the word out,
    whether long-form prose is out of fashion,
    or whether I&amp;rsquo;m barking up the wrong tree,
    but as &lt;a href=&#34;https://third-bit.com/2024/12/14/snailz/&#34;&gt;I wrote&lt;/a&gt; a couple of weeks ago,
    I&amp;rsquo;ve shelved &lt;a href=&#34;https://lessonomicon.github.io/rsdx/&#34;&gt;a planned follow-up&lt;/a&gt; as a result.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a related note,
    I wrote &lt;a href=&#34;https://lessonomicon.github.io/querynomicon/&#34;&gt;a tutorial on SQL&lt;/a&gt; for data scientists.
    I started a couple of others,
    but since I don&amp;rsquo;t have an audience or venue lined up,
    I doubt I&amp;rsquo;ll ever finish them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I ran &lt;a href=&#34;https://third-bit.com/t3/&#34;&gt;the teaching workshop&lt;/a&gt; a couple of times to raise money for &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rainbowrailroad.org/&#34;&gt;Rainbow Railroad&lt;/a&gt;,
    who need support now more than ever.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I appeared on the &lt;a href=&#34;https://codeforthought.buzzsprout.com/1326658/episodes/15010367-en-carpentries-for-all-greg-wilson&#34;&gt;Code for Thought&lt;/a&gt;,
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://open.spotify.com/episode/5wS3jB1d3Hq3hhWo4pFunA&#34;&gt;CoRecursive&lt;/a&gt;,
    and &lt;a href=&#34;https://pod.link/1602572955/episode/7de37354dfa00eb3308e523467f410aa&#34;&gt;Software Unscripted&lt;/a&gt; podcasts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I went to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.scipy2024.scipy.org/&#34;&gt;a conference&lt;/a&gt; for the first time since COVID
    and visited the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.capbridge.com/&#34;&gt;Capilano Suspension Bridge&lt;/a&gt; for the first time in fifty years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We wound down &lt;a href=&#34;https://neverworkintheory.org/&#34;&gt;It Will Never Work in Theory&lt;/a&gt; and wrote &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.computer.org/csdl/magazine/so/5555/01/10424425/1Ulj1Qa8tJ6&#34;&gt;a retrospective&lt;/a&gt; about it.
    I still post one-line summaries of interesting papers &lt;a href=&#34;https://third-bit.com/ideas/nwit/&#34;&gt;on this site&lt;/a&gt;,
    but after fourteen years,
    it was time to acknowledge that
    working programmers aren&amp;rsquo;t going to care about software engineering research in my lifetime,
    and that researchers aren&amp;rsquo;t going to care enough about that to change what they do or how they do it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I ran for the board of the Python Software Foundation and &lt;a href=&#34;https://third-bit.com/2024/07/01/psf-board-nomination/&#34;&gt;came seventh&lt;/a&gt;.
    In retrospect I&amp;rsquo;m not surprised:
    I haven&amp;rsquo;t really been involved in open source communities in years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I started playing the penny whistle,
    which is the only thing I&amp;rsquo;ve tried that doesn&amp;rsquo;t aggravate my tendon problems.
    I find the sound quite shrill compared to the tenor sax,
    but it&amp;rsquo;s definitely improving my lung capacity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I didn&amp;rsquo;t finish any of the children&amp;rsquo;s books I&amp;rsquo;ve been writing working on for the last few years,
    write any new short stories,
    or find a writing group in Toronto.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I took the family trailbiking for the first time,
    almost had my (regular) bike stolen,
    spent Thanksgiving at the cottage,
    and went to the gym less than I should have.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;row&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;col-2 col center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://third-bit.com/files/2024/bike-lock-2024-08-25.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;broken bike lock&#34; width=&#34;80%&#34;&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;col-2 col center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://third-bit.com/files/2024/ossai-sdxpy-2024-04.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Software Design by Example in Python&#34; width=&#34;80%&#34;&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;col-2 col center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://third-bit.com/files/2024/capilano-suspension-bridge-2024-07-14-c.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Capilano Suspension Bridge&#34; width=&#34;80%&#34;&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;col-2 col center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://third-bit.com/files/2024/trailbikes-2024-10-26-a.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;family on trail bikes&#34; width=&#34;80%&#34;&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;col-2 col center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://third-bit.com/files/2024/cottage-trail-2024-10-c.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;cottage trail&#34; width=&#34;80%&#34;&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;col-2 col center&#34;&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;What I Read&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Top of the list is Samantha Harvey&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://isbnsearch.org/isbn/9780802163622&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Orbital&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;,
which deserves all the praise it has been given—I can&amp;rsquo;t remember
the last time I read something so beautifully written.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;row&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;col-2 col center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://third-bit.com/files/2024/books/bohannon-eve.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Bohannon: Eve&#34; width=&#34;80%&#34;&gt;
    &lt;br&gt;
    Cat Bohannon: &lt;a href=&#34;https://isbnsearch.org/isbn/9780385350549&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Eve&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;col-2 col center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://third-bit.com/files/2024/books/brooks-cautious.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Brooks: The Cautious Traveller&#39;s Guide to the Wastelands&#34; width=&#34;80%&#34;&gt;
    &lt;br&gt;
    Sarah Brooks: &lt;a href=&#34;https://isbnsearch.org/isbn/9781250878618&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Cautious Traveller&#39;s Guide to the Wastelands&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;col-2 col center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://third-bit.com/files/2024/books/czerski-blue.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Czerski: The Blue Machine&#34; width=&#34;80%&#34;&gt;
    &lt;br&gt;
    Helen Czerski: &lt;a href=&#34;https://isbnsearch.org/isbn/9781324086345&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Blue Machine&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;col-2 col center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://third-bit.com/files/2024/books/davies-lying.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Davies: Lying for Money&#34; width=&#34;80%&#34;&gt;
    &lt;br&gt;
    Dan Davies: &lt;a href=&#34;https://isbnsearch.org/isbn/9781982114947&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Lying for Money&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;col-2 col center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://third-bit.com/files/2024/books/davis-girls.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Davis: The Good Luck Girls&#34; width=&#34;80%&#34;&gt;
    &lt;br&gt;
    Charlotte Nicole Davis: &lt;a href=&#34;https://isbnsearch.org/isbn/9781250299727&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Good Luck Girls&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;col-2 col center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://third-bit.com/files/2024/books/diehl-walls.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Diehl: Glass Walls&#34; width=&#34;80%&#34;&gt;
    &lt;br&gt;
    Amy Diehl: &lt;a href=&#34;https://isbnsearch.org/isbn/9781538170960&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Glass Walls&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;row&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;col-2 col center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://third-bit.com/files/2024/books/farmer-elderflora.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Farmer: Elderflora&#34; width=&#34;80%&#34;&gt;
    &lt;br&gt;
    Jared Farmer: &lt;a href=&#34;https://isbnsearch.org/isbn/9780465097845&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Elderflora&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;col-2 col center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://third-bit.com/files/2024/books/glenny-balkans.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Glenny: The Balkans&#34; width=&#34;80%&#34;&gt;
    &lt;br&gt;
    Misha Glenny: &lt;a href=&#34;https://isbnsearch.org/isbn/9781783784523&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Balkans&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;col-2 col center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://third-bit.com/files/2024/books/googins-transition.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Googins: The Great Transition&#34; width=&#34;80%&#34;&gt;
    &lt;br&gt;
    Nick Fuller Googins: &lt;a href=&#34;https://isbnsearch.org/isbn/9781668010754&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Great Transition&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;col-2 col center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://third-bit.com/files/2024/books/harrow-starling.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Harrow: Starling House&#34; width=&#34;80%&#34;&gt;
    &lt;br&gt;
    Alix Harrow: &lt;a href=&#34;https://isbnsearch.org/isbn/9783442206766&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Starling House&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;col-2 col center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://third-bit.com/files/2024/books/harvey-orbital.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Harvey: Orbital&#34; width=&#34;80%&#34;&gt;
    &lt;br&gt;
    Samantha Harvey: &lt;a href=&#34;https://isbnsearch.org/isbn/9780802163622&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Orbital&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;col-2 col center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://third-bit.com/files/2024/books/henderson-noises.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Henderson: A Book of Noises&#34; width=&#34;80%&#34;&gt;
    &lt;br&gt;
    Caspar Henderson: &lt;a href=&#34;https://isbnsearch.org/isbn/9780226823232&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;A Book of Noises&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;row&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;col-2 col center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://third-bit.com/files/2024/books/hershovitz-philosophy.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Hershovitz: Nasty, Brutish, and Short&#34; width=&#34;80%&#34;&gt;
    &lt;br&gt;
    Scott Hershovitz: &lt;a href=&#34;https://isbnsearch.org/isbn/9781984881830&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nasty, Brutish, and Short&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;col-2 col center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://third-bit.com/files/2024/books/house-consciousness.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;House: Nineteen Ways of Looking at Consciousness&#34; width=&#34;80%&#34;&gt;
    &lt;br&gt;
    Patrick House: &lt;a href=&#34;https://isbnsearch.org/isbn/9781250151179&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nineteen Ways of Looking at Consciousness&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;col-2 col center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://third-bit.com/files/2024/books/jimenez-spear.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Jimenez: The Spear Cuts Through Water&#34; width=&#34;80%&#34;&gt;
    &lt;br&gt;
    Simon Jimenez: &lt;a href=&#34;https://isbnsearch.org/isbn/9780593156612&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Spear Cuts Through Water&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;col-2 col center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://third-bit.com/files/2024/books/king-bookseller.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;King: The Bookseller of Florence&#34; width=&#34;80%&#34;&gt;
    &lt;br&gt;
    Ross King: &lt;a href=&#34;https://isbnsearch.org/isbn/9780802159830&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Bookseller of Florence&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;col-2 col center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://third-bit.com/files/2024/books/koenig-sorrows.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Koenig: The Dictionary of Obscure Sorrows&#34; width=&#34;80%&#34;&gt;
    &lt;br&gt;
    John Koenig: &lt;a href=&#34;https://isbnsearch.org/isbn/9781501153648&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Dictionary of Obscure Sorrows&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;col-2 col center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://third-bit.com/files/2024/books/liss-peculiarities.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Liss: The Peculiarities&#34; width=&#34;80%&#34;&gt;
    &lt;br&gt;
    David Liss: &lt;a href=&#34;https://isbnsearch.org/isbn/9781616963583&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Peculiarities&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;row&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;col-2 col center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://third-bit.com/files/2024/books/merchant-machine.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Merchant: Blood in the Machine&#34; width=&#34;80%&#34;&gt;
    &lt;br&gt;
    Brian Merchant: &lt;a href=&#34;https://isbnsearch.org/isbn/9780316487740&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Blood in the Machine&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;col-2 col center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://third-bit.com/files/2024/books/miro-monsters.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Miro: Ordinary Monsters&#34; width=&#34;80%&#34;&gt;
    &lt;br&gt;
    J.M. Miro: &lt;a href=&#34;https://isbnsearch.org/isbn/9781250833679&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ordinary Monsters&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;col-2 col center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://third-bit.com/files/2024/books/prasad-silk.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Prasad: Silk&#34; width=&#34;80%&#34;&gt;
    &lt;br&gt;
    Aarathi Prasad: &lt;a href=&#34;https://isbnsearch.org/isbn/9780063160255&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Silk&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;col-2 col center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://third-bit.com/files/2024/books/robeyns-limitarianism.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Robeyns: Limitarianism&#34; width=&#34;80%&#34;&gt;
    &lt;br&gt;
    Ingrid Robeyns: &lt;a href=&#34;https://isbnsearch.org/isbn/9781662601842&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Limitarianism&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;col-2 col center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://third-bit.com/files/2024/books/young-abolishing.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Young: Abolishing Fossil Fuels&#34; width=&#34;80%&#34;&gt;
    &lt;br&gt;
    Kevin Young: &lt;a href=&#34;https://isbnsearch.org/isbn/9798887440330&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Abolishing Fossil Fuels&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;col-2 col center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://third-bit.com/files/2024/books/zevin-tomorrow.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Zevin: Tomorrow, and Tomorrow, and Tomorrow&#34; width=&#34;80%&#34;&gt;
    &lt;br&gt;
    Gabrielle Zevin: &lt;a href=&#34;https://isbnsearch.org/isbn/9780593466490&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Tomorrow, and Tomorrow, and Tomorrow&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The Year to Come&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t expect to cross anything off &lt;a href=&#34;https://third-bit.com/2024/10/20/wish-list/&#34;&gt;my wish list&lt;/a&gt; this year,
but life is full of surprises.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My daughter will finish high school in June and leave home in August to start college.
    I don&amp;rsquo;t know how we&amp;rsquo;re going to fill our evenings and weekends without her,
    but I imagine we&amp;rsquo;ll finally get around to terracing our back yard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll be supervising some &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/gvwilson/browercast/&#34;&gt;undergrad&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/gvwilson/mossball/&#34;&gt;projects&lt;/a&gt; at the University of Toronto
    for the first time in 15 years.
    I&amp;rsquo;m also going to be speaking at &lt;a href=&#34;https://2025.cusec.net/&#34;&gt;CUSEC 2025&lt;/a&gt;;
    I hope this talk will age better than &lt;a href=&#34;https://third-bit.com/2024/12/01/never-look-back/&#34;&gt;my last one&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d really like to do an internship this summer.
    I understand why tech companies and universities and everyone else aren&amp;rsquo;t geared up for this,
    and I realize it would be unfair of me to take a position
    that might otherwise go to someone trying to start their career
    in the worst job market in my working lifetime,
    but it would be fun to be learning again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Record some videos for &lt;a href=&#34;https://third-bit.com/sdxpy/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Software Design by Example&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;?
    Maybe, but it&amp;rsquo;s a lot of work and I&amp;rsquo;m not sure who they would help.
    The same goes for writing some of &lt;a href=&#34;https://third-bit.com/ideas/not-on-the-shelves/2024/&#34;&gt;these books&lt;/a&gt;;
    I&amp;rsquo;d really like to cross one or two off the list,
    but see my note above about tech companies not realizing how much they need teachers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I probably won&amp;rsquo;t organize &lt;a href=&#34;https://third-bit.com/2024/10/28/what-would-be-in-a-new-aosa/&#34;&gt;another volume&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;a href=&#34;https://aosabook.org/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Architecture of Open Source Applications&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;,
    but if you want to, please &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:gvwilson@third-bit.com&#34;&gt;reach out&lt;/a&gt;:
    I&amp;rsquo;d be happy to offer advice and support.
    Similarly,
    I might finish &lt;a href=&#34;https://lessonomicon.github.io/webonomicon/&#34;&gt;this tutorial&lt;/a&gt; on human-scale web development if I can find a writing partner;
    please &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:gvwilson@third-bit.com&#34;&gt;email me&lt;/a&gt; if you&amp;rsquo;d like to help.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m going to keep trying to write fiction,
    but without peers to write for or the prospect of a market,
    it&amp;rsquo;s hard to stay motivated.
    The same holds for the penny whistle:
    if I don&amp;rsquo;t find a teacher or a group to play with, I probably won&amp;rsquo;t stick with it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Snailz</title>
   <link href="https://third-bit.com/2024/12/14/snailz/"/>
   <updated>2024-12-14T00:00:00Z</updated>
   <id>https://third-bit.com/2024/12/14/snailz/</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Earlier this year I put together notes for
a companion to the &lt;a href=&#34;https://third-bit.com/sdxjs/&#34;&gt;JavaScript&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://third-bit.com/sdxpy/&#34;&gt;Python&lt;/a&gt; versions of &lt;em&gt;Software Design by Example&lt;/em&gt;
aimed at &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Research_software_engineering&#34;&gt;research software engineers&lt;/a&gt;.
I shelved &lt;a href=&#34;https://lessonomicon.github.io/rsdx/&#34;&gt;the project&lt;/a&gt; because the (lack of) reaction to the first two books
convinced me that this isn&amp;rsquo;t what most people are looking for,
but I still hope that one of the software packages I built along the way might be useful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://pypi.org/project/snailz/&#34;&gt;Snailz&lt;/a&gt; is a set of &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Synthetic_data&#34;&gt;synthetic data generators&lt;/a&gt;
that simulate the collection, storage, and analysis of data related to
snails in the Pacific Northwest
that are growing unusually large as a result of exposure to pollution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One or more &lt;em&gt;surveys&lt;/em&gt; are conducted at one or more &lt;em&gt;sites&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Each survey collects &lt;em&gt;genomes&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;sizes&lt;/em&gt; of snails.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A &lt;em&gt;grid&lt;/em&gt; at each site is marked out to show the presence or absence of pollution.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Laboratory staff&lt;/em&gt; perform &lt;em&gt;assays&lt;/em&gt; of the snails&amp;rsquo; genetic material.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Each assay plate has a &lt;em&gt;design&lt;/em&gt; showing the material applied and &lt;em&gt;readings&lt;/em&gt; showing the measured response.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Plates may be &lt;em&gt;invalidated&lt;/em&gt; after the fact if a staff member believes it is contaminated.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first diagram below shows the schema of the database that holds the results;
the second shows how various scripts and parameter files interact
to create that database.
Along the way,
the scripts also create CSV files describing the designs of genomic assay plates
and both messy and tidy versions of readings for those plates.
The whole process is documented on &lt;a href=&#34;https://lessonomicon.github.io/snailz/&#34;&gt;the package site&lt;/a&gt;,
and all the code is open source.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://third-bit.com/files/2024/snailz-schema.svg&#34; alt=&#34;Database schema of snailz data&#34;&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Snailz database schema&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://third-bit.com/files/2024/snailz-workflow.svg&#34; alt=&#34;Workflow for generating snailz data&#34;&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Snailz data generation workflow&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>How It Will Be Used</title>
   <link href="https://third-bit.com/2024/12/14/how-it-will-be-used/"/>
   <updated>2024-12-14T00:00:00Z</updated>
   <id>https://third-bit.com/2024/12/14/how-it-will-be-used/</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I was a big proponent of MOOCs when they first emerged.
Why have thousands of teachers deliver mediocre lessons
when instead we could make the best teachers presenting the best content available to everyone?
It didn&amp;rsquo;t play out that way:
building and maintaining a good online course is difficult and expensive,
so almost everything we actually got was less effective than what we&amp;rsquo;d had.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However,
MOOCs did work well for three groups:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A minority of people are autodidacts capable of learning from just about anything.
    (I&amp;rsquo;ve heard their number put at one in seven, but can&amp;rsquo;t back that up.)
    I strongly suspect that most professional academics are in this group,
    which leads to a lot of survivor bias in judging MOOCs&amp;rsquo; success or failure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Right-wing political groups have long viewed teachers with hostility,
    particularly if those teachers are unionized.
    They won&amp;rsquo;t say
    &amp;ldquo;we can gut our opponents by deskilling their profession&amp;rdquo; in public,
    but &amp;ldquo;we have to embrace the future and it will save us money&amp;rdquo; serves the same end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And speaking of money,
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://third-bit.com/2014/03/14/learning-at-scale/&#34;&gt;I wrote in 2014&lt;/a&gt; that
    &amp;ldquo;learning at scale&amp;rdquo; is the same as &amp;ldquo;ubiquitous surveillance in the classroom&amp;rdquo;.
    I can&amp;rsquo;t talk about my direct experience of this,
    but LinkedIn didn&amp;rsquo;t buy Lynda because education is a profitable business;
    they spent 1.5 billion dollars in order to give employers even more information about job applicants.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During COVID,
what had once been a witty quote had turned into reality:
online education is what everyone wants for everyone else&amp;rsquo;s kids.
As public schools pushed more content online,
private after-school tutoring exploded.
Some of it is conspicuous consumption:
today&amp;rsquo;s middle-class parents humble-brag to each other
about how much they&amp;rsquo;re spending to get their kids into the right university
in the same way that they casually mention how much their latest home renovations cost.
But some of it,
I think,
stems from a growing sense of social insecurity.
More and more middle-class parents believe (rightly) that
their jobs and their children&amp;rsquo;s futures are at risk.
If poor kids can watch the same videos as yours,
then you&amp;rsquo;re going to start looking for some secret sauce that they can&amp;rsquo;t afford.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which brings us to AI in the classroom.
I&amp;rsquo;ve been using LLMs to help me with a bit of programming at work,
and I understand why people like &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.jonudell.net/&#34;&gt;Jon Udell&lt;/a&gt; are so excited by them:
they really do make it possible for non-experts to solve difficult problems
in a fraction of the time they would otherwise need.
My daughter isn&amp;rsquo;t exactly excited by them,
but frequently consults ChatGPT when she&amp;rsquo;s struggling through math homework,
in part because a third of the teacher&amp;rsquo;s solutions to practice problems are wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So yes,
I think AI has a lot of potential,
but I&amp;rsquo;d like to learn from my mistake with MOOCs.
In practice,
I think AI will be used to hollow out the teaching profession.
The Japanese call this &lt;em&gt;kūdōka&lt;/em&gt;,
and it inevitably widens the gap between haves and have-nots.
In a few years—ten, maybe, but not twenty—I expect that most low-income children
will be &amp;ldquo;learning&amp;rdquo; from bots
while what&amp;rsquo;s left of the middle class spend an ever-larger fraction of their income
on actual human teachers for their kids,
both because it produces better results
and to prove that they are, in fact, middle class.
Those who are profiting from this politically and financially
will point at the poor kids who succeed as proof that everyone could,
and those who saw the possibility but discounted the risk will still be telling themselves
that with just a bit more tinkering and a bit more funding
we might still reach the promised land.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope I&amp;rsquo;m wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If poor inner-city children consistently outscored children from wealthy suburban homes on standardized tests,
is anyone naive enough to believe that we would still insist on using these tests as indicators of success?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;– Kenneth Wesson, in Littky and Grabelle&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://isbnsearch.org/isbn/9780871209719&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Big Picture&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Long Evenings</title>
   <link href="https://third-bit.com/2024/12/10/long-evenings/"/>
   <updated>2024-12-12T00:00:00Z</updated>
   <id>https://third-bit.com/2024/12/10/long-evenings/</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;When my brother and I cleaned out my mum&amp;rsquo;s place,
I brought home a slab of fudge that she had made shortly before she died.
She was supposed to come to Ontario that month,
and my guess is that she&amp;rsquo;d planned to bring it for me as a surprise for my birthday.
I just ate the last piece of it,
and it reminded me of how long the evenings sometimes were when I was growing up.
The sun didn&amp;rsquo;t just set, at least not in the summer.
Instead,
the light ebbed little by little,
so gradually that you barely noticed it was getting darker
until something—a store closing or a light coming on in a window—made you realize
that another day had ended.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Time to make another cup of tea.
If you came in peace, be welcome.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Two Roads, and a Third</title>
   <link href="https://third-bit.com/2024/12/08/two-roads-and-a-third/"/>
   <updated>2024-12-08T00:00:00Z</updated>
   <id>https://third-bit.com/2024/12/08/two-roads-and-a-third/</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I caught up with some former colleagues this week,
and one of the questions that came up was,
&amp;ldquo;What would you do if you could have any job you wanted?&amp;rdquo;
I have two answers:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A &amp;ldquo;scholar in residence&amp;rdquo; position where I spend my time connecting people,
    mentoring junior colleagues and their projects,
    and generally trying to nudge the world (or at least my corner of our profession)
    in a slightly healthier direction.
    I&amp;rsquo;ve always enjoyed this,
    and while &lt;a href=&#34;https://aosabook.org/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Architecture of Open Source Applications&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    and &lt;a href=&#34;https://neverworkintheory.org/&#34;&gt;It Will Never Work in Theory&lt;/a&gt; didn&amp;rsquo;t become what I hoped they would,
    other ideas might.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A mid-level developer position building software for scientists.
    I say &amp;ldquo;for scientists&amp;rdquo; because it&amp;rsquo;s so rewarding,
    &amp;ldquo;building&amp;rdquo; because I miss being neck-deep in code,
    and &amp;ldquo;mid-level&amp;rdquo; because I&amp;rsquo;d really like to learn
    a few of the things that slid by me over the past twenty years.
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://gleam.run/&#34;&gt;Gleam&lt;/a&gt;?
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://htmx.org/&#34;&gt;htmx&lt;/a&gt;?
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://marimo.io/&#34;&gt;Marimo&lt;/a&gt;?
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.terraform.io/&#34;&gt;Terraform&lt;/a&gt;?
    It wouldn&amp;rsquo;t really matter as long as I felt every day
    that I understood something I hadn&amp;rsquo;t understood the day before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t think I could combine these two roles
because I always put programming to the side if I&amp;rsquo;m managing and networking.
I also think that it would be easier for me to get the first role than the second:
our industry doesn&amp;rsquo;t know what to do with people who want to take (what is viewed as)
a step down in their career for personal satisfaction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most surprising thing is that &amp;ldquo;teaching full-time&amp;rdquo; isn&amp;rsquo;t on my list
for the first time in two decades.
I built &lt;a href=&#34;https://lessonomicon.github.io/querynomicon/&#34;&gt;a tutorial on SQL&lt;/a&gt; earlier this year,
and started on three others,
but it feels a bit like wandering the halls in my old high school.
I don&amp;rsquo;t know anything well enough to teach it
that I didn&amp;rsquo;t already know ten or fifteen years ago;
while there&amp;rsquo;s a lot to be said for &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7xR50ty5DZ0&#34;&gt;playing the standards&lt;/a&gt;,
my daughter will be moving out in a few months to start college,
and I need to find something to occupy my mind when she does.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;p.s. one other thing I&amp;rsquo;d put on the wish list is an office within cycling distance.
I miss being able to grab a coffee with my co-workers once or twice a week…&lt;/p&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Software Engineering Management Books</title>
   <link href="https://third-bit.com/2024/12/03/software-engineering-management-books/"/>
   <updated>2024-12-03T00:00:00Z</updated>
   <id>https://third-bit.com/2024/12/03/software-engineering-management-books/</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I have read the following recent-ish books about software engineering management
(or in a few cases, read the first couple of chapters and just skimmed the rest).
For the most part they treat the Silicon Valley model as a given,
and if they touch on things like labor rights
or what systemic discrimination reveals about how the system actually works,
they do so only in passing.
If you know of other books that are specifically about managing software development teams,
were published after 2010,
and grapple with &lt;a href=&#34;https://third-bit.com/2018/11/24/afraid-of-change/&#34;&gt;things VCs would rather not talk about&lt;/a&gt;,
I&amp;rsquo;d be grateful for pointers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Marianne Bellotti: &lt;a href=&#34;https://isbnsearch.org/isbn/9781718501188&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Kill It With Fire&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (2021)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sarah Drasner: &lt;a href=&#34;https://isbnsearch.org/isbn/9798986769318&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Engineering Management for the Rest of Us&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (2022)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Camille Fournier: &lt;a href=&#34;https://isbnsearch.org/isbn/9781491973899&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Manager&amp;rsquo;s Path&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (2017)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Claire Hughes Johnson: &lt;a href=&#34;https://isbnsearch.org/isbn/9781953953216&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Scaling People&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (2023)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cate Huston: &lt;a href=&#34;https://isbnsearch.org/isbn/9781098154066&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Engineering Leader&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (2024)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Will Larson: &lt;a href=&#34;https://isbnsearch.org/isbn/9781732265189&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;An Elegant Puzzle&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (2019)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Will Larson: &lt;a href=&#34;https://isbnsearch.org/isbn/9781736417911&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Staff Engineer&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (2021)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Edmond Lau: &lt;a href=&#34;https://isbnsearch.org/isbn/9780996128100&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Effective Engineer&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (2015)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gergely Orosz: &lt;a href=&#34;https://isbnsearch.org/isbn/9789083381824&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Software Engineer&amp;rsquo;s Guidebook&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (2023)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tanya Reilly: &lt;a href=&#34;https://isbnsearch.org/isbn/9781098118730&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Staff Engineer&amp;rsquo;s Path&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (2022)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Matthew Skelton and Manuel Pais: &lt;a href=&#34;https://isbnsearch.org/isbn/9781942788812&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Team Topologies&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (2019)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;James Stanier: &lt;a href=&#34;https://isbnsearch.org/isbn/9781680507249&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Become an Effective Software Engineering Manager&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (2020)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Andrew Swerdlow: &lt;a href=&#34;https://isbnsearch.org/isbn/9798988984917&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Tech Leadership&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (2023)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Merih Taze: &lt;a href=&#34;https://isbnsearch.org/isbn/9798985349900&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Engineers Survival Guide&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (2021)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Peter Wendorff: &lt;a href=&#34;https://isbnsearch.org/isbn/9781484273791&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Politics in Software Development&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (2022)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Never Look Back</title>
   <link href="https://third-bit.com/2024/12/01/never-look-back/"/>
   <updated>2024-12-01T00:00:00Z</updated>
   <id>https://third-bit.com/2024/12/01/never-look-back/</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I gave a keynote at &lt;a href=&#34;http://cusec.net/&#34;&gt;CUSEC&lt;/a&gt; in 2010 about evidence-based software engineering.
A recording was available on Vimeo for several years,
but it disappeared some time after 2016.
A few days ago,
though,
I got mail out of the blue from someone who had found a copy.
They shared it with me in case I wanted to post it somewhere,
so I downloaded it and watched it through,
and now I feel a little bit sad.
In increasing order:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lot of what I said was wrong,
    either because the claims I made were stronger than they should have been
    or because the science itself has turned out to be flawed.
    (Stereotype threat, anyone?)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was rude to a couple of people in order to get laughs from the audience.
    I don&amp;rsquo;t expect any of them will read this,
    but if they do,
    I&amp;rsquo;m sorry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I really did believe things would get better.
    They haven&amp;rsquo;t:
    students don&amp;rsquo;t learn any more about research practices or empirical results in software engineering today
    than they did fifteen years ago,
    and programmers in industry are just as oblivious as they ever were.
    I really did think that &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.oreilly.com/library/view/making-software/9780596808310/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Making Software&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.computer.org/csdl/magazine/so/2024/03/10424425/1Ulj1Qa8tJ6&#34;&gt;It Will Never Work in Theory&lt;/a&gt;
    would have an impact on more than a few scattered individuals;
    I&amp;rsquo;m disappointed that they didn&amp;rsquo;t.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll post the video in a few days,
but I honestly found parts of it hard to watch.
I&amp;rsquo;ll be speaking at CUSEC again in January;
here&amp;rsquo;s hoping that talk holds up better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Time to make another cup of tea.
If you came in peace, be welcome.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>More Student Project Proposals</title>
   <link href="https://third-bit.com/2024/12/01/more-student-project-proposals/"/>
   <updated>2024-12-01T00:00:00Z</updated>
   <id>https://third-bit.com/2024/12/01/more-student-project-proposals/</id>
   <content type="html"></content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Another Static Site Generator for Lessons</title>
   <link href="https://third-bit.com/2024/11/30/another-ssg-for-lessons/"/>
   <updated>2024-11-30T00:00:00Z</updated>
   <id>https://third-bit.com/2024/11/30/another-ssg-for-lessons/</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I built a very simple static site generator (SSG) called &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/lessonomicon/mccole&#34;&gt;McCole&lt;/a&gt;
to support the lessons I mentioned in &lt;a href=&#34;https://third-bit.com/2024/11/24/unfinished-projects/&#34;&gt;my previous post&lt;/a&gt;.
I could have stuck with &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dmulholl.com/docs/ark/main/&#34;&gt;Ark&lt;/a&gt;
(which I use to build this site and books like &lt;a href=&#34;https://third-bit.com/sdxpy/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Software Design in Python&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;),
but writing my own helped me figure out what I actually need,
and might someday serve as the basis for a tutorial of some sort.
In no particular order, &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/lessonomicon/mccole&#34;&gt;McCole&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s features are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Read configuration from the project&amp;rsquo;s &lt;code&gt;pyproject.toml&lt;/code&gt; file.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Convert all the Markdown files in or below the project&amp;rsquo;s root directory to HTML
    using &lt;a href=&#34;https://jinja.palletsprojects.com/&#34;&gt;Jinja&lt;/a&gt; templates.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rename a few files along the way:&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;README.md&lt;/code&gt; becomes &lt;code&gt;index.html&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;CODE_OF_CONDUCT.md&lt;/code&gt; becomes &lt;code&gt;code_of_conduct.html&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;CONTRIBUTING.md&lt;/code&gt; becomes &lt;code&gt;contributing.html&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;LICENSE.md&lt;/code&gt; becomes &lt;code&gt;license.html&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create an HTML page corresponding to every source code file
    so that (for example) &lt;code&gt;a/b.py&lt;/code&gt; is visible online as &lt;code&gt;a/b.py.html&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Replace &lt;code&gt;https://third-bit.com&lt;/code&gt; at the start of URLs with the relative path to the site&amp;rsquo;s root directory.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Replace links to Markdown files with links to the corresponding HTML files.
    I do this so that links would work properly when people view the Markdown files on GitHub.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rewrite the URL in something like &lt;code&gt;[label](b:key)&lt;/code&gt; to &lt;code&gt;[label](https://third-bit.com/bibliography.html#key)&lt;/code&gt;
    to make it easy for authors to link to bibliographic citations.
    These special links &lt;em&gt;don&amp;rsquo;t&lt;/em&gt; work when files are viewed on GitHub,
    but it&amp;rsquo;s a lot less typing that the alternative.
    (I use the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/dmulholl/shortcodes&#34;&gt;shortcodes&lt;/a&gt; package to do this with &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dmulholl.com/docs/ark/main/&#34;&gt;Ark&lt;/a&gt; sites,
    but after a bit of experimentation I decided to special-case these links in &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/lessonomicon/mccole&#34;&gt;McCole&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Similarly,
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/lessonomicon/mccole&#34;&gt;McCole&lt;/a&gt; rewrites &lt;code&gt;[term](g:key)&lt;/code&gt; to &lt;code&gt;[term](https://third-bit.com/glossary.html#key)&lt;/code&gt;
    so that authors can easily insert glossary references.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If a page contains any glossary references,
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/lessonomicon/mccole&#34;&gt;McCole&lt;/a&gt; creates a list of defined terms at the top of the page.
    (In my experience,
    this is the most useful way to tell a would-be instructor what the lesson is actually about.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I tried using shortcodes to format figures consistently,
    but once I decided not to use them for the glossary and bibliography,
    it didn&amp;rsquo;t seem worth keeping them for figures.
    Instead,
    I check their properties during linting (see below).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;My tutorials focus on programming,
    so I need to be able to include snippets of source code in pages.
    &amp;ldquo;Snippets&amp;rdquo; makes the problem more complex:
    I often want to include just one function or a couple of methods rather than an entire source file.
    My previous SSG had a couple of hundred lines of code
    to pull sections out of source files in various ways;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/lessonomicon/mccole&#34;&gt;McCole&lt;/a&gt; just checks that the text in the Markdown file
    is contained in the source file.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/lessonomicon/mccole&#34;&gt;McCole&lt;/a&gt; defines a class for each inclusion like &lt;code&gt;language-py&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;language-sql&lt;/code&gt;
    so that inclusions from different languages can be styled differently.
    I haven&amp;rsquo;t included syntax highlighting,
    partly because I want to keep this SSG simple
    but also because the highlighting rules I choose probably &lt;em&gt;won&amp;rsquo;t&lt;/em&gt; match what learners see
    in their editor or IDE.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/lessonomicon/mccole&#34;&gt;McCole&lt;/a&gt; includes a tool for linting sites,
    i.e.,
    for checking that links resolve,
    glossary entries are mentioned somewhere,
    and so on.
    It turned out to be a lot simpler to check for problems
    than to generate correct content automatically,
    at least for small lessons.
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/lessonomicon/mccole&#34;&gt;McCole&lt;/a&gt; also uses &lt;a href=&#34;https://pypi.org/project/html5validator/&#34;&gt;html5validator&lt;/a&gt;
    to check the formatting of the HTML pages it generates;
    specific lessons use tools like &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.astral.sh/ruff/&#34;&gt;ruff&lt;/a&gt; to check source code as well.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what &lt;em&gt;doesn&amp;rsquo;t&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/lessonomicon/mccole&#34;&gt;McCole&lt;/a&gt; include that a full-featured lesson SSG would?
The most important thing is probably some sort of support for exercises:
styling them,
numbering them,
keeping track of solutions,
and so on.
I could also add CSS styling for various kinds of callouts,
but I&amp;rsquo;m not trying to reproduce something like &lt;a href=&#34;https://carpentries.github.io/workbench/&#34;&gt;the Carpentries Workbench&lt;/a&gt;:
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/lessonomicon/mccole&#34;&gt;McCole&lt;/a&gt; is a multi-bit screwdriver,
not a fully-equipped machine shop.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Unfinished Projects</title>
   <link href="https://third-bit.com/2024/11/24/unfinished-projects/"/>
   <updated>2024-11-24T00:00:00Z</updated>
   <id>https://third-bit.com/2024/11/24/unfinished-projects/</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Things I haven&amp;rsquo;t finished:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A &lt;a href=&#34;https://lessonomicon.github.io/querynomicon/&#34;&gt;tutorial on SQL&lt;/a&gt; for data scientists&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A &lt;a href=&#34;https://lessonomicon.github.io/sudonomicon/&#34;&gt;tutorial on systems programming&lt;/a&gt; for data scientists&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A &lt;a href=&#34;https://lessonomicon.github.io/webonomicon/&#34;&gt;tutorial on web programming&lt;/a&gt; for data scientists&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A &lt;a href=&#34;https://gvwilson.github.io/doris/&#34;&gt;tutorial on building a dashboard engine&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A &lt;a href=&#34;https://lessonomicon.github.io/mccole/&#34;&gt;very simple static site generator&lt;/a&gt; for the projects listed above&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Another volume of &lt;a href=&#34;https://aosabook.org/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Architecure of Open Source Applications&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Another 15 examples focused on concurrency for &lt;a href=&#34;https://third-bit.com/sdxpy/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Software Design by Example in Python&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://gvwilson.github.io/rsdx/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Research Software Design by Example&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (a follow-on to &lt;a href=&#34;https://software-carpentry.org/&#34;&gt;Software Carpentry&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A &lt;a href=&#34;https://lessonomicon.github.io/snailz/&#34;&gt;synthetic data generator&lt;/a&gt; for the project above&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://third-bit.com/mrsp/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Managing Research Software Projects&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (another follow-on to &lt;a href=&#34;https://software-carpentry.org/&#34;&gt;Software Carpentry&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://third-bit.com/btt/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Building Tech Together&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (advice for students doing their first team project)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Data Science for Software Engineers&lt;/em&gt; (which doesn&amp;rsquo;t currently have an online home)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/roc-lang/book-of-examples&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Software Design by Example in Roc&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (to explore functional programming)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://third-bit.com/fiction/beneath-coriandel/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Beneath Coriandel&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (an adult fantasy novel told from multiple viewpoints)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://third-bit.com/fiction/booksters-apprentice/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Bookster&amp;rsquo;s Apprentice&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (a YA novel set in the same world)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://third-bit.com/fiction/still-book/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Still&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (a YA novelette based on &lt;a href=&#34;https://third-bit.com/fiction/still-short/&#34;&gt;this short story&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://third-bit.com/fiction/madica/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Madica&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (a middle-grade story about fairies, ninja cats, and robot dinosaurs)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://third-bit.com/fiction/maddy-roo/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Maddy Roo&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (a middle-grade story about furries and robots)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Iffy&lt;/em&gt; (a YA novel about a girl growing up in a post-Melt Antarctica)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;All the Other Santas&lt;/em&gt; (featuring RoboSanta, Clausbeard the Pirate, Zombie Claus, and others)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I should be working on:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Re-doing the slides for &lt;a href=&#34;https://third-bit.com/sdxpy/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;SDXPY&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and recording a 30-minute video for each chapter&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Trying to get &lt;a href=&#34;https://third-bit.com/fiction/beneath-coriandel/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Beneath Coriandel&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://third-bit.com/fiction/booksters-apprentice/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Bookster&amp;rsquo;s Apprentice&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;https://third-bit.com/fiction/still-book/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Still&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; published&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finishing &lt;em&gt;Iffy&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;All the Other Santas&lt;/em&gt;, or the sequel to &lt;em&gt;Maddy Roo&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Trying (again) to write &lt;a href=&#34;https://third-bit.com/ideas/sdgc/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sex and Drugs and Guns and Code&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I&amp;rsquo;ve learned about myself:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I have lots of ideas, most of which don&amp;rsquo;t make as much sense to other people as they do to me.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I start things before I&amp;rsquo;ve thought them through.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I have trouble finishing things (largely because of #2).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I enjoy tinkering with small pieces of software much more than I enjoy contributing to large ones.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I enjoy teaching and mentoring more than I enjoy managing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I run out of steam when I&amp;rsquo;m working on my own or don&amp;rsquo;t have a specific audience and deadline.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Project Students</title>
   <link href="https://third-bit.com/2024/11/21/project-students/"/>
   <updated>2024-11-21T00:00:00Z</updated>
   <id>https://third-bit.com/2024/11/21/project-students/</id>
   <content type="html"></content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Milner on Invention</title>
   <link href="https://third-bit.com/2024/11/18/milner-on-invention/"/>
   <updated>2024-11-18T00:00:00Z</updated>
   <id>https://third-bit.com/2024/11/18/milner-on-invention/</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I was a PhD student, I attended a talk by the late Robin Milner where he said two things that have stuck with me.
The first, I repeat quite often.
He argued that credit for an invention did not belong to the first person to invent something
but to the first person to explain it well enough that no one needed to invent it again.
His first historical example was Leibniz publishing calculus and then Newton claiming he invented it first:
it didn&amp;rsquo;t matter if he did or not,
he failed to explain it to anyone and so the fact that Leibniz needed to independently invent it was Newton&amp;rsquo;s failure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— &lt;a href=&#34;https://mastodon.social/@david_chisnall@infosec.exchange/113503287934765521&#34;&gt;David Chisnall&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>What Worked Last Time?</title>
   <link href="https://third-bit.com/2024/11/10/what-worked-last-time/"/>
   <updated>2024-11-10T00:00:00Z</updated>
   <id>https://third-bit.com/2024/11/10/what-worked-last-time/</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m going to ask a favor, but I need to tell a story first.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back in 2017,
in the wake of Trump&amp;rsquo;s first inauguration and the Muslim travel ban,
I tried to get a bunch of people to write a chapter each for
&lt;a href=&#34;https://third-bit.com/ideas/sdgc/&#34;&gt;a book&lt;/a&gt; that would explain basic ideas in politics, economics, and justice to programmers.
The model had succeeded before:
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.oreilly.com/library/view/beautiful-code/9780596510046/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Beautiful Code&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.oreilly.com/library/view/making-software/9780596808310/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Making Software&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;,
and &lt;a href=&#34;https://aosabook.org/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Architecture of Open Source Applications&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
were all widely read,
so I thought something that covered regulatory capture,
how it is that &amp;ldquo;intellectual&amp;rdquo; became &amp;ldquo;property&amp;rdquo;,
why people routinely vote against their own interests,
and so on would find an audience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The project never really got off the ground.
The programmers who volunteered to help didn&amp;rsquo;t really know the subjects themselves
(though a couple of them tried valiantly to learn as much as they could in a hurry).
As for the social scientists I approached,
they were either too busy with their own projects,
(quite reasonably) wanted to be paid,
or simply didn&amp;rsquo;t know how to talk to people in tech
with essentially no background in the humanities.
Their idea of &amp;ldquo;basic&amp;rdquo; was what they would teach in freshman college course;
unfortunately,
most programmers are at a tenth-grade level
when it comes to understanding how society works.
In fact it&amp;rsquo;s worse than that:
most programmers (including me) know as little about politics and economics
as the average political science major knows about recursion,
but we &lt;em&gt;think&lt;/em&gt; we know a lot more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So here we are eight years later.
I think it&amp;rsquo;s more important than ever
to offer an accessible, compelling alternative
to the self-serving libertarian brogrammer bullshit that is
Silicon Valley&amp;rsquo;s default setting,
but before I break my &amp;ldquo;no new projects&amp;rdquo; rule and try to get something off the ground,
I&amp;rsquo;d like to ask the favor I mentioned at the start of this post.
If you were part of something post-2016 that actually had an impact in tech,
I&amp;rsquo;d be very grateful if you could &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:gvwilson@third-bit.com&#34;&gt;let me know&lt;/a&gt;
what you did,
what it changed,
and how you know.
The Ford Foundation&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.fordfoundation.org/work/learning/learning-reflections/keeping-those-on-the-front-lines-of-change-safe-five-years-of-the-ford-foundation-grantee-safety-program/&#34;&gt;Grantee Safety Program&lt;/a&gt; is a great example:
thank you in advance for pointers to others.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
</feed>